Eugene B. Bowen Papers MS030
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Eugene B. Bowen Papers
1875 -- 1964
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Bowen, Eugene B.
MS030
0.5 Linear Feet 1 letter size document box
Arrangement
This collection is organized into two series: Subject Files and Memorabilia.
Custodial History
Half of the collection was donated Martha Jennisonin 2001, the other half consisted of three folders originally part of the Vertical Files.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence from 1908-1964, photographs, negatives, postcards and memorabilia. The subjects of the correspondence include honorary degrees, trustee business, dedications, building proposals for the theater and bridges at Tufts, Adams High School, chimes, Mr. Bowen's last will and other personal and business topics. There are also newspaper clippings including his obituary.
Biographical / Historical
Eugene Bucklin Bowen (1855-1952), E1876, was a benefactor and lifetime trustee of Tufts. His gifts include the Bowen Lions outside Barnum Hall, Bowen Gate, and the Bowen Chimes.
Born in Adams, Massachusetts, on November 22, 1855, Bowen moved to Cheshire, Massachusetts, before beginning high school. He was the son of Henry C. Bowan and Susan Elizabeth Bucklin. At Tufts, Bowen held the only remunerative position the college had to offer a student at that time, ringing the old College Bell on top of Ballou Hall. While he had intended to provide Tufts with a new, larger bell, the Class of 1898 presented the college with such a bell at their tenth reunion. Bowen was also manager of the Tufts football team. After being one of fourteen men to graduate from the School of Engineering in 1876, Bowen briefly served as principal of the high school in Adams, Massachusetts, before returning to work at his father's hay and grain business for the rest of his professional career.
A faithful attendant of Tufts' commencement exercises and alumni days, Bowen presented the college with a pair of lion statues to stand guard outside of Barnum Museum in 1923, and donated the Bowen Gate in 1925. He also provided the funds for the memorial tablets of Hosea Ballou and Austin B. Fletcher, one of his classmates, at the north entrance of Ballou Hall, while sponsoring the construction of the columned porch at that entrance. During alumni festivities, Bowen, a descendant of eleven Revolutionary War soldiers, would don the uniform of the color guard of the Massachusetts State Society, Sons of the American Revolution, and parade around the campus with a replica of the 1776 Bennington Battle flag.
In 1924, Bowen was made a life trustee of the college. The class of 1926 invited him to be an honorary member of their class, to honor his loyalty to Tufts on the fiftieth anniversary of his graduation. He had been the organizer and past president of the Berkshire Tufts Club, in addition to his duties as a trustee. 1926, he donated a set of chimes to be played from the tower of Goddard Chapel.
Bowen died April 19, 1952, at his home in Cheshire, following a long illness. At the time of his death, he was the oldest living Tufts alumnus, and the only living member of the class of 1876.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Bowen, Eugene B.; Alumni and alumnae --Benefactors; Bowen Lions; Bowen Gate; Bowen Chimes; University history
- Subject Files, 1908 -- 1964; MS030.001; 0.5 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains subject files including correspondence relating to Mr. Bowen and Tufts and papers concerning Mr. Bowen's last will as well as his obituaries. Most letters were written by Mr. Bowen to members of the Tufts community including University presidents and fellow trustee. Topics include recommendations for honorary degrees, dedications and building projects, and trustees issues.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged by subject and chronology.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Corrrespondence, 1908 -- 1922; MS030.001.001.00001 (Box MS030 Shared 1)
  - Corrrespondence, 1923; MS030.001.001.00002 (Box MS030 Shared 1)
  - Corrrespondence, 1924; MS030.001.001.00003 (Box MS030 Shared 1)
  - Corrrespondence, 1925 -- 1926; MS030.001.001.00004 (Box MS030 Shared 1)
  - Corrrespondence, 1927 -- 1929; MS030.001.001.00005 (Box MS030 Shared 1)
  - Corrrespondence, 1930 -- 1931; MS030.001.001.00006 (Box MS030 Shared 1)
  - Corrrespondence, 1932 -- 1933; MS030.001.001.00007 (Box MS030 Shared 1)
  - Corrrespondence, 1934 -- 1935; MS030.001.001.00008 (Box MS030 Shared 1)
  - Corrrespondence, 1936 -- 1939; MS030.001.001.00009 (Box MS030 Shared 1)
  - Corrrespondence, 1940 -- 1964; MS030.001.001.00010 (Box MS030 Shared 1)
  - Corrrespondence and material re last will and obituaries, 1929 -- 1953; MS030.001.001.00011 (Box MS030 Shared 1)
    This file concerns Mr. Bowen's bequest to the university and obituary biographical information.
- Memorabilia, 1875 -- 1941; MS030.002; 1.7 Linear Feet
  This series includes memorabilia relating to Mr. Bowen and Tufts. This series includes the 1876 commencement program and invitation; the printed transcript of the inauguration of University President Elmer Hewitt Capen in 1875; a postcard picturing Eaton Memorial Library; Mr. Bowen's exams prepared at Adams High School and shared with Tufts Faculty; two reunion questionnaires.
  There are two folders. One contains photographs, the other contains documents.
  - Memorabilia, 1875 -- 1941; MS030.002.001.00012 (Box MS030 Shared 1)
    This file includes Mr. Bowen's commencement program and invitation stationary from 1875.
  - Photographs/ Negatives, 1941; MS030.002.001.00013 (Box MS030 Shared 1)
    This file contains a silver gelatin print of Mr. Bowen as a young man. There are other commemorative pictures as well, including a picture of a celebration for the 50th anniversary of the founding of the College.
  - Signed photograph of Bowen, 1926; MS030.002.001.00014 (Box Shared 46)
    This photograph is not part of the original accession; it was found uncatalogued in the stacks in summer 2007.